Guide to the Carr Family Collection of Travel Sketches, Scrapbooks, and Genealogical Material
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Scrapbooks, notebooks, and genealogical material, Series II
  - Thomas William Carr scrapbook, circa 1819-1899; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; 1 volume (468 pages); 36 x 25 cm (Box Oversize 9)
    Album is titled in gilt on the spine: "Carr M.S.S. Scraps."
    Notes at the front, signed "T.W.C.", remark that the album was "rebound & enlarged in 1889," and "the first vol. begun perhaps 10 years before and also the folio volume." The notes suggests that the current scrapbook was compiled later than the others, although presumably all three were put together by Reverend Thomas William Carr of Barming. His obituary, from December 1912, is included in the scrapbook's final pages. It is clear that leaves 229-234 were added later, since they are of different paper from the rest of the album.
    In general (though there are many exceptions), the material in this scrapbook seems to date from the lifetime of Thomas William Carr of Barming, coming from his immediate ancestors or relatives, and descendents. Occasionally, later descendents have added material from the mid or late 20th century. The volume also seems focused on personal documents (rather than the legal documents collected in volume 1 of the earlier folio scrapbook). It especially includes family and portrait photographs, photos and engravings of houses and churches associated with the family, personal letters, the family coat of arms, genealogies, and death notices, memorial inscriptions, and photos of tombs. There are also letters from those with whom T.W. Carr of Barming corresponded in his attempts to gather information and documents for his family history. In many places, T.W. Carr of Barming has helpfully penned in notes explaining the provenance of a document or its relation to the Carr family. However, the album itself is not clearly organized and follows no narrative structure. It has a loose chronological arc, but there are also 16th century documents on the purchase of Eshott Heugh estate in the final pages of the book.
    Affixed to the inside of the back cover is a collection of wax seals. Most appear to date to the 1800s, with a handful perhaps from the 1600s.
    Seals (artifacts); Photographs; Correspondence; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; Carr family
  - Laura Carr (Lady Cranworth) scrapbook, circa 1839-1870; Cranworth, Laura Rolfe, Lady, 1807-1868; 1 volume (96 pages); 30 x 24 cm (Box Oversize 10)
    The scrapbook has a leather label on front cover reading "L.C. Scraps" and a calling card on the back cover reading "Lansdowne Place: Miss Carr." The scrapbook is structured tête-bêche, so that it begins from both front and back covers, with blank pages in the middle. This suggests that at least two people contributed material to the book. Given the "L.C." in the title and the material's content, one probable compiler of the book was Laura Carr (1807-1868), who was the daughter of Thomas William Carr (1770-1829) and married Robert Monsey Rolfe (1790-1868) (created Baron Cranworth in 1850). A number of elaborate Valentines addressed to "Laura" are included, plus various newspaper articles about Lord Cranworth (who twice served as Lord Chancellor). Most of the material specifically related to Laura occurs in the first half of the scrapbook, which is considerably more personal, and includes Valentines, love poems, riddles, letters, and sketches. The second half consists largely of newspaper clippings and printed engravings (most from after Laura's death).
    Dates of the material suggest that the scrapbook was begun from the front cover (probably by Laura), and that someone began adding material from the back after Laura Carr's death in 1868. Laura could not have contributed all of the front material, however, since the notices on Charles Dickens' death post-date her, while one final item, an etching, is labeled "given to me by Margaret Wilson in London in 1871." It may be that the second compiler initially began adding material to the front, and then decided to flip the scrapbook around. This person may also have pasted the upside-down bookplate to the back cover reading "Miss Carr Lansdowne Place." It is possible the unidentified contributor is Laura's older sister Fanny Carr, who lived until 1880 and by 1872 was the only surviving sibling.
    Scrapbooks; Carr, Frances Rebecca, 1796-1880; Cranworth, Robert Monsey Rolfe, Baron, 1790-1868; Cranworth, Laura Rolfe, Lady, 1807-1868
  - The history of the family of Carr of Dunston Hill, Co. Durham: and the collateral lines in England / by Colonel Ralph Edward Carr ... and by Cuthbert Ellison Carr (C.E.). London: Mitchell and Hughes, 1893-1899., Carr, Ralph Edward, 1833-1892; 3 volumes: illustrations; 38 cm (Box Oversize 11-13)
    The copy was owned by Thomas William Carr (of Barming), and includes his significant annotations and corrections, along with inserted correspondence, photographs, and sketches (by Anna Margaret Carr).
    Genealogies; Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; Carr family
  - Eshott Heugh notebook: volume 1, 1881-1899; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; 1 volume (138 pages); 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Thomas William Carr kept two notebooks, both stamped Eshott Heugh in gilt on the cover, which served in part as personal journals, as well as records of the Carr family and the Eshott estate.
    The first notebook includes material from 1881 to about 1899, and includes: notes on the Eshott Heugh estate, including comments relating to its magnetic and astronomical position made by the royal astronomer; a history of the estate and its owners; notes on visitors to the estate; sketches of memebers of the Carr family; and the history of various pieces of furniture at the estate.
    While most of the notebook appears to be the work of Thomas William Carr, shorter sections were also written by Robert Lancelot Carr (b. 1863) and Frank Carr.
    Diaries; Carr family; Carr, Robert Lancelot, b. 1863; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912 -- Diaries; Carr, Frank, b. 1870; Eshott House (Alnwick, England)
  - Eshott Heugh notebook: volume 2, 1899-1912; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; 1 volume (circa 200 pages, with blanks); 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    The second of the two Eshott Heugh notebooks resumes in 1899. Like the first, it serves as a journal for Thomas William Carr, and also includes: more family history; Carr family coats of arms; notes on maintenance of the estate; notes on social visits and the weather; verse; and letters written to Carr. The end of the volume includes an index (to both notebooks).
    Diaries; Carr family; Eshott House (Alnwick, England); Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912 -- Diaries
  - Diary of Harriet Carr (Deacon), 1869; Carr, Harriet, 1829-1889; 1 volume (42 pages, with blanks); 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    The first part of the diary describes a family holiday to Bath and Lynmouth in August and September 1869. Harriet describes her family's enjoyment of the beach and natural scenery of the area. The family took several day trips to nearby locations, where Harriet purchased some souvenirs, including photographs.
    The second part describes the family's journey to France and Italy from 24 November to 10 December, 1869. Harriet provides sketches of Roman history when recording her observations of sites such as a Coliseum. She also describes in detail the architectural qualities of various churches that they visited in France and Italy.
    Diaries; Carr, Harriet, 1829-1889 -- Diaries; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912
  - Armorial notebook: with Carr genealogy, 1878-1902?; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; 1 volume (46 pages, with numerous items tipped in or laid in); 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    The compiler of the notebook is unrecorded, but it is probably Thomas William Carr (of Barming). Most of the contents concern the coats of arms of the Carr family, and those of related families. The volume includes manuscript notes, assorted printed material (tipped in), engravings of coats of arms, drawings of arms (many colored), and letters to Thomas William Carr.
    Devices (Heraldry); Coats of arms; Armorials; Carr family
  - Chart shewing the descendants of Thomas William Carr of Eshott Heugh. London: Mitchell and Hughes, 1887., 1 volume (1 sheet); 55 x 77 cm, folded to 30 x 20 cm (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
    Three copies of a genealogical chart, privately printed in December, 1887. The chart documents the Carr family of Eshott Heugh beginning with the marriage of Thomas William Carr to Frances Morgan (a match which resulted in eight children, many of whom feature prominently in the present collection).
    All three copies are annotated (to varying degrees) by Thomas William Carr (of Barming). The first copy includes minimal additional information concerning T.W. Carr's own entry, that of his wife Harriet, and that of his sister Lucy Emily.
    The second copy has 10 additional pages bound in (preceding the chart) in which Carr has written out a series of genealogical tables showing the descent of the Ellison and Woodward branches of the Carr family. Interspersed are biographical notes on members of the family. Also laid in to this section is a photographic reproduction of a portrait miniature of Matthew Carr Hexham.
    The third and final copy contains the most prolific additions. These include: several printed pedigrees of the Carr family, from unidentified sources; manuscript notes on Carr arms, mottos, and genealogical matters; a heavily annotated version of the title genealogical chart; several pages of notes, much later, recording "Egerton-Warburton Cousins"; and a printed chart showing the "Pedigree of Bonner of Newcastle-on-Tyne."
    Genealogies; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; Carr family
  - Probate of the last will and testament and four codicils of Margaret Lewen Morton, spinster deceased: dated at Durham the 20th day of August 1823., 1823 August 20; 1 sheet (on vellum); 58 x 64 cm (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Margaret was the sister of Frances Morton, and the great-aunt of the Rev. Thomas William Carr of Barming.
    The will has a seal affixed to it, presumably that of the Bishop of Durham. In the will, Margaret makes an array of small bequests of money and personal items to her female family members and close female friends. A note affixed to the will by a clerk records that she named her brother-in-law, Thomas William Carr, as her executor.
    Wills; Carr, Thomas, 1733-1793; Morton, Margaret Lewin, d. 1823
  - Carr family documents and letters, 1788-1894; 22 items; 25 x 20 cm, and smaller (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence and printed documents or forms. The items were collected in a contemporary file labeled "Documents & old letters relating to the Carrs: photographs and paintings." They are now removed to a new folder; the original is retained.
    The authors of the correspondence are varied and largely unidentified. Recipients include the Lord Bishop of Cloyne, Miss Edgeworth; Harriet Carr (nee Deacon); Mrs. H. L. Carr; and Mr. Thomas Woodward.
    Documents include: a newspaper clipping narrating the naval feats of Sir C. Ogle of Kirkley, a member of the Ogle branch of the Carr family; the certificate of baptism of Thomas William Carr, 1801; the marriage certificate of Thomas William Carr and Harriet Deacon; death certificate of Susan Carr, 1834; the marriage certificate of Mark William Carr and Elizabeth Collinson, 1 December 1788; and the will of Frances Carr's father, 1798.
    Correspondence; Carr family
  - The raid of the Kers, by the Ettrick Shepherd. [London]: Thomas Kell, 1876., Hogg, James, 1770-1835; 1 volume ([6], 27, [3], v, [1] p., [8] leaves of plates); 26 cm (Box 2, Folder 10)
    A ballad, by James Hogg, originally published in Blackwood's Magazine, December, 1830. Lithographically reproduced. The final 8 pages contain "Notes with armorial bearings of the ancient family of Ker."
    The present copy was owned by Thomas William Carr of Barming. It includes, tipped in at end, two letters from R. Thompson (?) concerning the book.
    Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; Carr family
  - Christ the believer's life: a sermon preached in the church of Teddington, Middlesex, on Sunday, July 13, 1834, on occasion of the lamented death of Susan, the beloved wife of the Rev. T.W. Carr ... By the Rev. James Hough, A.M. ..., Hough, James, d. 1847; 1 volume ([4] p., p. 251-278); 19 cm (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Printed sermon on the occasion of the death of Susan Carr. Given the page numbering in the present volume, it appears that the sermon was once part of a larger collection. The binding of the present copy is gilt-stamped. T.W.C.
    The copy appears to have belonged to multiple members of the Carr family, including Thomas William Carr, Harriet Carr, and Elizabeth Carr. Affixed to the rear pastedown is a lithographed portrait of an unidentified woman, almost certainly Susan Carr. Opposite the portrait is noted, "The etching [sic] and sermon were done at her mother's expense. Letter of T.W.C."
    Sermons; Carr, Susan Hamilton, d. 1834
- Photographs, etc., Series III
  - Album of Carr family portrait photographs, 1865-1899; 1 volume (46 photographs); 16 x 13 cm (Box Oversize 14)
    Comprises portrait photographs of individual members of the Carr family. The inside front cover of the album is inscribed: "The Children of T.W. Carr, Rector of Barming." Mounts of the photographs have been labeled in a single (much later?) hand. The majority of photographs appear to be albumen prints.
    The album includes portraits of T.W. Carr, Harriet Carr, Mary Carr, Thomas Carr, Robert Carr, Al (Alured) Carr, Laura Carr, Frank Carr, and Margaret Carr. The first photograph depicts Barming Rectory (with Carr family members in the foreground).
    Albumen prints; Photographs; Portraits; Carr family
  - Framed images, 19th century; 3 items (Box Oversize 15)
    Includes a framed tintype photograph of a young girl in a dress carrying a basket of flowers. The image depicts Mary Joanna Sophia Carr, the eldest child of the Rev. Thomas William Carr (of Barming).
    The second image is a silhouette portrait, perhaps lithographed, of a middle-aged man. The subject is probably the family patriarch, the eldest Thomas William Carr.
    The third and final framed image is a small portrait, drawn in graphite, of Margaret Lewen Morton. A note on the reverse reads: "Copied by Miss Ethel Baruster (?) from one belonging to Mr Russell of Hatchford. A fair copy, but the lower part of the nose is larger than the original."
    Graphite drawings; Silhouettes; Tintypes (prints); Portraits; Carr, Thomas, 1733-1793; Carr, Mary Joanna Sophia, b. 1859; Morton, Margaret Lewin, d. 1823
  - Photographs of the Carr family at Barming and Linnington, circa 1876-1931?; 20 photographs: albumen and b&w; 20 x 15 cm, and smaller (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Loose photographs, collected in a contemporary file labeled "Old family photographs, and Carrs at Barming & Linnington." The photographs have been removed to a new folder; the original is retained.
    Many of the photo subjects or sitters are unidentified. There are several photographs of painted portraits of Carr ancestors. Identifiable subjects include: Marjorie Fitzherbert (1907 and 1910/1911); William Carr (from a painting, 1709); Frank Collett Carr(?); Harriet Carr (?); and the Eshott Heugh property.
    Portraits; Albumen prints; Photographs; Travel photography; Carr family
  - Photographs of the Carr family, Late 19th century?; circa 50 photographs: albumen and b&w prints; 19 x 12 cm, and smaller (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Loose photographs, collected in a contemporary file labeled "Documents & old letters relating to the Carrs: photographs and paintings." The photographs have been removed to two new folders; the original file is retained.
    Many of the photo subjects or sitters are unidentified. There are numerous photographs of painted portraits of Carr ancestors. Identifiable people include: Thomas Carr, d. 1793 (painting); Thomas Woodward, Sheriff of Bristol, 1636 (painting); Frances Carr, née Morton; Arthur Saplé Webb; T.W. Carr in 1838; a sketch by Andrew Morton of T.W.C. circa 1825; Francis Woodward MD at Bath; Rebecca Carr (painting); Sarah Morton (painting); Sir William Ogle (painting); and Margaret and Lucy Carr at St. John's College, 1890.
    Identifiable places (in the second folder) include: the Pont Marengo in the French town of Carcassonne; San Sebastian, Interior de la Iglesia Santa Maria; Bayonne, la Théatre; Cairo (?); Haddon Hall; several beach scenes, including Biarritz; the Crescent, Buxton; and Ludchurch.
  - Engravings of prominent homes in Northamptonshire and Northumberland, mid-19th century; 11 engravings; 20 x 13 cm, and smaller (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Engravings collected in a contemporary file labeled "Documents & old letters relating to the Carrs: photographs and paintings." The engravings are now removed to a new folder; the original is retained.
    Subjects depicted include: Chipchase Castle, Northumberland, seat of John Reed; Wollaton, Northamptonshire in 1667; Rushton Hall, Northamptonshire, seat of the Hon. Mr. C. Medlycott; Kirby Hall, Northamptonshire; Bamborough Castle, Northumberland; Heaton Hall, seat of Sir Matthew White Ridley; Tynemouth Priory; Faxton Chapel, Northampton; and Battle Stone, or Percy Cross, Northumberland.
    Engravings; Country homes -- Great Britain; Northumberland (England); Northamptonshire (England)
  - Webb family photographs, circa 1930-1980; 26 photographs (Box 3, Folder 15)
    The items were housed in a file labeled "Webb Family Snaps and L.J.W. at Various Stages of her Career. Australian Family and Friends." They are now removed to a new folder; the original is retained.
    The photos depict members the Webb family of Australia, an offshoot of the Carr family. Some of the family members pictured here may be related to those named in genealogical tables drawn in the 1960s or 1970s labeled as "Egerton-Warburton Cousins" which feature in Item 7. Also included are a few newspaper and magazine clippings that feature members of the Webb family and a program for a funeral service and an informational pamphlet about St. David's, Wales.
    Photographs; Webb family